Switching to a plant-based diet has been
shown to achieve better outcomes
than those reported for conventional
treatments for Crohn’s disease
and ulcerative colitis.
Check out the video.
"The Best Diet for Ulcerative Colitis
and Crohn’s Disease Treatment"
One of the most common questions
physicians treating patients
with inflammatory bowel disease
(IBD) are asked is whether
changing one's diet can positively
affect the course of their disease?
Traditionally, our answer
had been, "We have no clue,"
but this may now be changing,
given the evidence that hydrogen
sulfide may be playing
a role in ulcerative colitis.
And since the sulfur-containing
amino acids concentrated in meat
cause an increase in colonic
levels of this rotten egg gas,
maybe we should take off the meat.
See, animal protein isn't just associated
with an increased risk of getting
inflammatory bowel disease
in the first place, but also IBD
relapses once you have the disease.
This is a recent development. Because
the concept of IBD as a lifestyle disease
mediated mainly by a Westernized diet
is not widely appreciated, an analysis
of diet in the follow-up period after
diagnosis in relation to a relapse
of inflammatory bowel disease has
been ignored. But not any longer.
Ulcerative colitis patients in remission
and their diets were followed for a year
to see which foods were linked to the
bloody diarrhea coming raging back.
And the strongest relationship between
a dietary factor and an increased risk
of relapse observed in this study
was for a high intake of meat.
So, what if you have people lower
their sulfur-containing amino acid intake
by decreasing their consumption
of animal products? They tried it
on four ulcerative colitis patients,
and without any change in meds,
they experienced like a four-fold
improvement in their loose stools.
In fact, they felt so much better
that they didn't think it ethical
to try switching them back.
Since sulfur-containing amino acids are
the primary source of dietary sulfur,
a low sulfur diet essentially means
a shift from a typical diet high
in animal protein and fat, and low in
fiber, to more of a plant-based diet.
Westernized diets
are pro-inflammatory,
and plant-based diets
are anti-inflammatory.
Let's see what treatment with
a plant-based diet can do, after
the onset of ulcerative colitis during
a low-carbohydrate weight-loss diet.
A 36-year-old man lost 13
pounds on a low-carb diet,
but also lost his health,
diagnosed with ulcerative colitis.
Put him on a diet centered around
whole plant foods, though,
and poof—symptoms resolved
without medication. Okay, but this is
just one case. I mean, case reports
are like glorified anecdotes.
The value of case reports lies in
their ability to inspire researchers
to put it to the test, and
that's exactly what they did.
There had never been a study published,
focusing on using plant-based diets
for the treatment of
ulcerative colitis until now.
Considering the lack of a suitable
diet to be the biggest issue faced
in the current treatment of
inflammatory bowel disease,
and regarding it as a lifestyle disease
caused mainly by our omnivorous diet,
a group of Japanese gastroenterologists
have been providing a plant-based diet
to all patients with IBD for over a
decade, and publishing extraordinary
results, far better than have to date
been reported in the medical literature.
I profiled some of the early work in
one of my first videos that went up
on NutritionFacts.org, found to
be effective in the maintenance
of remission in Crohn's disease
by 100% at one year,
90% at two years.
So how about a plant-based diet for
relapse prevention in ulcerative colitis?
Educational hospitalization meant
bringing patients into the hospital
to control their diet
and educate them
about the benefits
of plant-based eating,
so they'd be more motivated
to continue it at home.
Most patients—about three-quarters—
experienced improvements
such as disappearance or decrease
in bloody stool during hospitalization.
Fantastic! Okay, but here's the
really exciting part. Then they followed
the patients for 5 years, and 81%
were able to remain in remission
the whole time, and 98% were able to keep
the disease at bay for at least a year.
I mean that blows other treatments away.
Those relapse rates are far lower
than those reported with medication.
Under conventional treatment, other
studies found that about half relapse,
compared to only 2% among
those taught to eat healthier.
A plant-based diet was previously shown
to be effective in both the active and
quiescent stages of Crohn's disease.
The current study has shown that a
plant-based diet is effective in both
the active and quiescent stages
of ulcerative colitis as well.
And so they did another study on
even more severely affected cases
with active disease
and found the same thing,
far beating out
conventional drug therapy.
People felt so much better, they
were still eating more plant-based
even 6 years later.
The researchers conclude that
a plant-based diet is effective
for treating ulcerative colitis
to prevent a relapse.
Why? Well, plant-based diets are rich
in fiber, which feeds our good gut bugs.
That might partly explain why
a plant-based diet prevents
a variety of chronic diseases.
And so that's what we may be seeing
with inflammatory bowel disease,
suggesting that replacing an omnivorous
diet with a plant-based diet
is the right approach. It's like using
plant-based diets to treat
the cause of heart
disease, our #1 killer.
Not just safer and cheaper,
but works better.
No adverse side effects
noted for plant-based eating.
Let's compare that to the side
effects of immunosuppressants
used for ulcerative colitis, like
cyclosporine. Side effects include...
And now we have even fancier drugs
that cost about $60,000 a year
that s $5,000 a month and
they don't even work very well,
with clinical remission at 1 year
of only like 17 to 34%.
And instead of no adverse side
effects, they can give you a stroke.
They can give you heart failure.
They can even give you cancer,
including a rare type of cancer
that often results in death.
Or how about a serious brain disease
known as progressive multifocal
leukoencephalopathy,
which can kill you,
and for which there is
no known treatment or cure.
Yeah, yeah, increased risk of death,
but did we mention how nice and small
the pill was and the easy-to-open bottle?
Important to our understanding
and prevention of the global increase
in inflammatory bowel disease, we know
that dietary fiber appears to reduce risk,
whereas dietary fat, animal protein,
and sugar may increase risk.
"Despite the recognition of the
westernization of lifestyle as
a major driver of the growing incidence
of inflammatory bowel disease,
no countermeasures against such lifestyle
changes have been recommended,
except that patients with Crohn's
disease shouldn't smoke."
Look, we know consuming
whole, plant-based foods
is synonymous with an
anti-inflammatory diet.
Here's a list of foods
with inflammatory effects;
here's a list of foods with
anti-inflammatory effects.
So how about putting a
plant-based diet to the test?
Just cutting down on red and
processed meat didn't work,
but what about cutting
down on all meat?
A 25-year-old guy diagnosed
with Crohn's disease,
but failed to enter clinical remission
despite standard medical therapy.
But after switching to a diet based
exclusively on grains, legumes—
like beans, split peas, chickpeas,
and lentils—vegetables, and fruits,
he entered clinical remission,
without the need for medication
and showed no signs of Crohn's
disease on follow-up colonoscopy.
It's worth delving into
some of the details.
The conventional treatment they started
him on is infliximab, sold as REMICADE,
which can cause a stroke, and may
increase your chances of getting
lymphoma and other cancers—but
it's a bargain for only $35,000 a year.
And it may not even work
in 35 to 40% of patients,
and that seemed to be the case
here, so they upped the dose
after 37 weeks, and still suffering
after two years on the drug—
until he tried completely eliminating
animal products and processed foods
from his diet—finally experiencing
a complete resolution of his symptoms.
Prior to this, his diet had
been a typical American diet.
But having experienced complete
clinical remission for the first time
since his diagnosis, he decided
to switch to a whole-food,
plant-based diet permanently, severely
reducing his intake of processed food
and limiting animal products
to one serving, or less, per week.
And whenever his diet started to slip,
symptoms started coming back.
But he could always wipe
them out by eating healthier.
After six months of implementing
these changes in diet and lifestyle,
including stress relief and exercise,
a follow-up demonstrated complete
mucosal healing of the gut lining with
no visible evidence of Crohn's disease.
We know a diet consisting of whole
grains, legumes, fruits, and vegetables
has been shown to be helpful in the
prevention and treatment of heart
disease, obesity, diabetes,
hypertension, gallbladder disease,
rheumatoid arthritis,
and many cancers.
Although further research is required,
this case report suggests
that Crohn's disease might be
added to this list of conditions.
But that further research
has already been done!
About 20 patients with Crohn's disease
were placed on a semi-vegetarian diet,
meaning no more than a half-
serving of fish once a week
and a half-serving of meat
once every two weeks,
and achieved 100% remission rate
at one year, and 90% at two years.
Some strayed from the diet though.
Let's see what happened to them.
After a year, half had relapsed, and at
year two only 20% remained in remission.
But those that stuck with
it had remarkable success.
It was a small study with
no formal control group,
but represents the best reported
result in Crohn's relapse prevention
published in the medical
literature to date.
Nowadays, Crohn's patients are often
treated with so-called biologic drugs,
expensive injected antibodies that
suppress your immune system
and have effectively induced
and maintained remission
in Crohn's disease,
but not in everyone.
The current remission rate in Crohn's
with early use of REMICADE: 64%.
So 30 to 40% of patients are likely to
experience a disabling disease course
even after treatment. So what
about adding a plant-based diet?
Remission rates jumped up to 100%
for those who didn't have to drop out
due to drug side effects. Even
if you exclude the milder cases,
100% of those with serious, even severe
fulminant disease achieved remission.
But if you look at gold standard
systematic reviews, they conclude
that the effects of dietary interventions
on inflammatory bowel diseases,
Crohn's disease and ulcerative
colitis, are uncertain.
This is because only randomized
controlled trials were considered.
Totally understandable, as that's
the most rigorous study design.
Nevertheless, people with inflammatory
bowel disease deserve advice
based on the 'best available evidence'
rather than no advice at all.
And switching to a plant-based diet
has been shown to achieve
far better outcomes than those
reported on conventional treatments
in both active and quiescent stages
in both Crohn's and ulcerative colitis.
For example, here's one-year
remission rates in Crohn's disease:
100% compared to budesonide, an
immunosuppressant corticosteroid drug;
a half elemental diet, meaning
like at-home tube feedings;
the $35,000 a year drug REMICADE;
or the $75,000 a year drug Humira.
Safer, cheaper, and more effective?
Maybe we should recommend plant-based
diets for inflammatory bowel disease.
It would seem clear that treatment
based on treating the cause
of the disease is optimal.
Spreading the word about healthier
diets could help halt the scourge
of inflammatory bowel, but how
are people going to hear about
this amazing research without some
kind of public education campaign?
That's what NutritionFacts.org
is all about.